{"tossups": [{"question": "Members of this party allegedly received kickbacks from Swedish arms company Bofors AB. Shortly before a planned interview with Peter Ustinov, one leader of this party was assassinated in retaliation for ordering Operation Blue Star; that leader of this party suspended civil liberties during the Emergency. In a 2014 election, this party lost power to Narendra Modi\u2019s BJP. For ten points, name this political party whose members have included Jawaharlal Nehru and Indira Gandhi.", "answer": "<b> Indian National Congress</b> (or<b> INC</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "James T. Brady and this man were part of the legal defense team that helped Daniel Sickles get an acquittal for the murder of Philip Barton Key II. This man entered his most famous position after the resignation of Simon Cameron over calls to arm slaves. Upon Lincoln\u2019s death, this man either said that he belongs to the \u201cages\u201d or \u201cangels.\u201d This politician\u2019s dismissal was found in violation of the Tenure of Office Act. For ten points, name this Secretary of War during the 1860s whose dismissal by Andrew Johnson led to his impeachment.", "answer": "Edwin<b> Stanton</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This event was investigated by Alden Smith, which found that it could be attributed to an \u201cact of God.\u201d Benjamin Guggenheim died in this event, to which the<em> Mount Temple</em> reacted immediately, but the<em> Californian</em> ignored the rockets and Morse code signals. Other fatalities of this event included John Jacob Astor, but not Molly Brown, who later called herself \u201cunsinkable.\u201d For ten points, name this April 1912 disaster in which a White Star liner on her maiden voyage struck an iceberg and sank.", "answer": "the<b> sinking</b> of the RMS<b> Titanic</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One portrait of this man depicts him alongside Jesus with the caption \u201cI have chosen him.\u201d This man kept the head of one enemy in his closet, and, on the suspicion that another of his enemies could transform into animals, he ordered all black dogs to be put to death. The Fort Dimanche [dee-mahnsh] massacre was carried out by this man, and Clement Barbot was put to death by this man\u2019s Tonton Macoutes. For ten points, name this \u201cPresident for Life\u201d of Haiti, whose nickname referred to his background as a physician.", "answer": "Fran\u00b8cois<b> Duvalier</b> (or<b> Papa Doc</b> Duvalier)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A portrait of this man depicts him in a blue-green vest with gold buttons, sitting at a polished table with a needle and pair of burins. This artisan honored the \u201cglorious ninety-two\u201d in a bowl commemorating resistance to the Townshend Acts and commissioned by the Sons of Liberty. He was depicted with his left hand holding a not-yet-engraved teapot by portraitist John Singleton Copley. For ten points, name this Boston silversmith and patriot whose midnight ride was the subject of a Longfellow poem.", "answer": "Paul<b> Revere</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Fowzi Nejad managed to survive this event when his executor realized he was on live TV. The sound of mice was used to justify the sound of bugging devices on the walls in this event that saw Red and Blue teams rappel through the roof. Trevor Lock tackled the perpetrator of this event, Oan Ali Mohammed. It began when the disgruntled Khuzestani DRFLA took 26 people hostage, and was ended by SAS troops. For ten points, name this 1980 hostage crisis in London that took place in a diplomatic building staffed by the government of Ayatollah Khomeini.", "answer": "<b> Iranian Embassy siege</b> (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In this year, an article was published accusing Lenin of being a German agent, prompting the massacre of Bolsheviks in the July Days. Order No. 1 was issued during this year, which hampered the disastrous Summer Offensive launched by Alexander Kerensky in this year. One event in this year involved mass protests on Women\u2019s Day, and the Provisional Government was created in this year after Grand Duke Michael refused to take his brother\u2019s throne. The February and November Revolutions occurred in, for ten points, what year, in which Tsar Nicholas II abdicated and the Bolsheviks established the Soviet Union?", "answer": "<b> 1917</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "During one event held in one of these locations, a photograph was taken of one major world leader poking another leader in the chest; that location was in Sokolniki Park in Moscow. In that 1959 event described by this word, one participant bragged about having color televisions in his country. A group described by this word was scandalized by an affair in which members of this group snubbed the wife of its Secretary of War John Eaton. For ten points, name this word describing Andrew Jackson\u2019s cabinet as well as a debate between Nikita Khrushchev and Richard Nixon.", "answer": "<b> kitchen</b>s (accept<b> Kitchen</b> Debate; accept<b> Kitchen</b> Cabinet) Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A 1967 police mutiny in this country killed 27 British troops, after which the British briefly left the Crater District. 800,000 workers of this country were expelled from Saudi Arabia after this nation refused to back intervention in the Gulf War. 40% of this country\u2019s population adheres to the Zaidi sect of Islam. This country\u2019s northern and southern divisions were unified under Ali Abdullah Saleh. This country has been in civil war since Abd Rabbuh Mansur Hadi was ousted by Houthi rebels. For ten points, name this country on the southern tip of the Arabian Peninsula whose capital is Sana\u2019a.", "answer": "<b> Yemen</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "One side at this battle had landed at Arzila. This battle took place by the Loukkos river, and Thomas Stukley was killed via cannonball early in this battle. One side was encouraged to fight this battle after successes at Mazagan and Tangier, and Ahmed al-Mansur rose to prominence after this battle. This battle occurred after Abu Abdallah requested aid against the Ottoman-backed Abd al-Malik. It spawned the myth that the slain king Sebastian would one day return to lead his people. For ten points, name this 1578 victory for Morocco over Portugal that ended the Aviz dynasty.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Three Kings</b> (or the Battle of<b> Ksar El Kebir</b> or Battle of<b> Oued el Makhazaeen</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A leader of this sect wrote an autobiography of his exile which is translated as \u201cLife.\u201d A community founded by this sect at Vietka was deported after Catherine the Great conquered the region. This sect insisted on making the sign of the cross with two fingers rather than three. This sect\u2019s formation is known as<em> raskol</em>, and was born after reforms made by Patriarch Nikon reverted all the churches literature back to the original Greek. For ten points, name this religious denomination that refused to accept reforms made by the Russian Orthodox Church.", "answer": "<b> Old Believer</b>s (accept<b> Old Ritualist</b>s; accept<b> starovyery</b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s response, when the conviction for living on Native American territory for Samuel Worcester was made void, was supposedly \u201cJohn Marshall has made his decision, now let him enforce it.\u201d After this man signed the Force Law, the South Carolina state legislature ended the Nullification Crisis, but his refusal to renew the charter of the Second Bank of the United States led to the Panic of 1837. For ten points, name this seventh U.S. president, nicknamed \u201cOld Hickory.\u201d", "answer": "Andrew<b> Jackson</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This event was a response to the clubbing of Cager Lee and the use of lethal force by James Bonard Fowler. During this event, Jim Clark deputized all white men over the age of 21. Outrage over the death of Jimmie Lee Jackson was channeled into this event, which was followed a month later by \u201cTurnaround Tuesday.\u201d Amelia Boynton suffered greatly from a tear gas attack during this event. For ten points, name this event in which police officers brutally attacked a group, led by Martin Luther King, that was marching from Selma to Montgomery, Alabama.", "answer": "<b> Bloody Sunday</b> (accept<b> march from Selma to Montgomery</b>, prompting on partial answers, before \u201cmarch\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man commissioned Carlisle Castle to defend his country\u2019s northern border. This monarch seized the land of Edgar Atheling which prompted an invasion of his country by Malcolm III. This man led an army against Robert de Mowbray after the latter refused to attend his court. A stone named for this ruler reads \u201cHere stood the oak tree, on which an arrow shot by Sir Walter Tyrell at a stag, glance and struck this [man].\u201d William the Conqueror was the father of, for ten points, what second Norman King of England?", "answer": "<b> William II</b> (accept<b> William Rufus</b>; accept<b> William the Red</b>; prompt on William; do not accept William II of Normandy)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man co-sponsored a bill with Emanuel Celler that closed loopholes in the Clayton Antitrust Act. With Oren Harris, he helped reform the FDA after the thalidomide</b> <b>controversy. Lyndon Johnson, Al (+)</b> <b>Gore Sr., and this man were the three Southern</b> <b>senators who refused to sign the Southern Manifesto; Gore joined this man in his state\u2019s delegation to Congress. This enemy of (*)</b> pornography and comic books also headed a committee to investigate Mafia members Joe Adonis and Frank Costello. For ten points, name this man, a 1956 Vice Presidential candidate with Adlai Stevenson, who served two and a half terms as a senator from Tennessee.", "answer": "Estes<b> Kefauver</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man wrote that \u201cthe test tube and the microscope are needed rather than ax and rifle\u201d in a paper arguing for the importance of education. William Appleman Williams\u2019book</b><em><b> The Tragedy of American Diplomacy</b></em><b> argued that one of this man\u2019s ideas encouraged American imperialism in Asia. The results of the (+) 1890 census caused this man to write his most famous paper, which was presented at the Chicago Columbian Exposition of 1893 and argued that the (*)</b> abundance of land on the American continent allowed for the development of American democracy. For ten points, name this historian whose essay \u201cThe Significance of the Frontier in American History\u201d expounded his \u201cFrontier Thesis.\u201d", "answer": "Frederick Jackson<b> Turner</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Since the victims of this event gave the perpetrators of this event lodging and food for ten days before this event took place, this event was considered to be a particularly heinous crime known as \u201cmurder under trust.\u201d Robert Duncanson ordered Robert Campbell to</b> <b>ensure that \u201cthe (+)</b> <b>old fox and his cubs do upon no account escape\u201d while carrying out</b> <b>this event. John Dalrymple, Master of Stair, planned this event, which occurred because Alasdair MacIain failed to swear an oath of allegiance by a January 1st deadline to King (*) </b> William III. For ten points, name this 1692 massacre of 38 members of the MacDonald clan in the Scottish Highlands.", "answer": "<b> Glencoe</b> Massacre Page 10", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>The passage of this law was hastened by a migration to the south caused by a devastating 1877-78 drought known as the Grande Seca. Joaquim Nabuco was one of the leading proponents for this law. The power of fazendas (+) declined as a result of this law, leading to increased support among the oligarchs for a coup that put Deodoro da Fonseca in power. This legislation was preceded by the Law of Sexagenarians and the Law of the (*) </b>Free Womb. It was signed into law by Princess Isabel, who was ruling as regent in place for her father, Pedro II. For ten points, name this 1888 law that banned slavery in Brazil.", "answer": "<b> Golden</b> Law (or Lei<b> Aurea</b>; prompt on \u201cBrazil\u2019s anti-slavery law\u201d before \u201cslavery\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}